Finding Aid for the Michael and Susan Kahn Collection of Political Cartoons LSC.2419
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 1. American Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1798-2020; Series 1; 24.2 linear feet (14 boxes, 1 map folder)
  - Photographic portrait of Thomas Nast [Carte-de-visite], circa 1870; Carte de visite, a black and white portrait photograph print mounted on thick paper card and trimmed down to approximately 2 1/4" x 3 7/8". (Box 132, Folder 4)
    Carte de visite of Thomas Nast by Napoleon Sarony printed on thick paper.
  - Still Standing [Photographic print of window (possibly in New York City) showing 9/11 reaction cartoon with Manhattan skyline and Uncle Sam's legs as the Twin Towers], circa 2001; 1 Photographic Print (Box 132, Folder 5)
    Print of photo depicting a cartoon displayed in a window showing New York City after 9/11, smoke billowing from lower Manhattan as the legs of what appears to be Uncle Sam stand in place of the Twin Towers (World Trade Center), his clenched fist visible as well. The caption reads: "Still standing. Thanks to all the police, firemen, and volunteers of this fine country."
  - Tax Tales, The Game, circa 1996; 1 Board game. Board game in box. Box has been somewhat damaged as it was previously stacked under books. (Box 132, Folder 9)
  - The Domestic Blockade [Carte-de-visite], 1863 (Box 132, Folder 3)
  - The Ins and Outs, circa 1884; 1 Drawing. Ink on paper drawing with publication notations for newspaper on verso. Paper in poor condition. Significant mildew and staining - especially at edges. (Box 132, Folder 12)
  - The President's Speech (Illustrated by Nineteen Artists), 1944; 1 Speech. 2 copies. (Box 132, Folder 7)
    Includes text of speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt given on September 23, 1944 - "The President's Speech Opening His Campaign. Made Before the Teamsters Union on September 23rd, 1944 Illustrated by Nineteen Artists."
  - [Untitled John Branch editorial cartoon, published in San Antonio Express-News in 2008. Debate Expectations - 2008 Republican VP candidate Sarah Palin pole vaulting with GOP elephant jumping with excitement], 1 Print. Inscribed in ink below drawing: To Mike, a fellow cartoon enthusiast with regards - John Branch (Box 119, Folder 5)
  - "And If Elected..." The Art and Politics of Thomas Nast [poster], 1984; 1 Poster. Possible mold. Some folds and wrinkling. Some small holes at edges. Edges torn,some corner portions missing. (Folder 507)
    Exhibition poster for "The Art and Politics of Thomas Nast" at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco / Achenbach Foundation for Graphic Arts (San Francisco, C.A.) June 30through September 3, 1984.
    Depicts "Another Such Victory, and I am Undone" - Pyrrhus from Harper's Weekly March 24, 1877. Wood engraving of bruised and battered elephant sitting with sling on one leg, bandages on head, trunk and other parts of body, and a crutch sitting nearby; a small piece of the elephant's tail is on the ground. A gravestone in background notes "Here Lies Democratic TIger - Greatly Mourned by the Bereaved Filibusters."
  - Achtung Baby! [poster], circa 2005; 1 very large poster, folded and wrinkled at edges. (Folder 507)
    Depicts Arnold with quote from his film Pumping Iron. Inscribed by artist in black ink.
  - Andrew Jackson (from life by Wm. Brown), 1844; 1 Lithograph. Paper mounted onto thick board. (Folder 507)
    Silhouette profile portrait of Andrew Jackson standing near a tree overlooking a valley with a stately home in the distance.
  - LBJ Political Cartoons: The Public Years [poster], 1987; 1 large poster, previously rolled, some folds on corners. Some wear and tear. (Folder 507)
    Exhibition poster for "LBJ Political Cartoons: The Public Years" at the Lyndon Baines Johnson Library & Museum November 7, 1987 through February 28, 1988.
  - The Billy Ireland Cartoon Library and Museum Grand Opening Festival of Cartoon Art, November 14-17, 2013 University Libraries [poster], 1 Poster. 2 copies in plastic. (Folder 507)
  - The Bloody Massacre perpetrated in King Street, Boston on March 5th, 1770 by a party of the 29th REG. Engraved, Printed and Sold by Paul Revere. [poster], circa 2000; 1 Print (Folder 507)
    Historical Reproduction CP-701-a
  - The Political Pen of David Levine [poster], 1984; 1 Poster. Possible mold. Some folds and wrinkling. Some small holes at edges. (Folder 507)
    Exhibition poster for "The Political Pen of David Levine" at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco / Achenbach Foundation for Graphic Arts (San Francisco, C.A.) June 30 through September 3, 1984.
  - View of Washington City, 1971; 1 Lithograph (Folder 507)
    Reprint of 1859 lithographic print depicting view of Washington, D.C. with U.S. Capitol Building in the foreground.
  - Assassination of President Lincoln (At Ford's Theatre) Washington, D.C., April 14th 1865), circa 1865; 1 Broadside. All edges missing pieces, very brittle. (Box 76, Folder 1)
    Depiction of President Lincoln's assassination.
  - British Warfare in 1812, 1837-38., 1838; 1 Lithograph (Box 76, Folder 1)
    Political cartoon to garner anti-British sentiment in reaction to the 1837 "Caroline affair" and the Canadian independence movement. Subsequently, the incident led to the "Caroline test" legal principle still applied today (anticipatory self-defense) to international law.
  - The Chicago Platform, What Is It, Peace or War., 1864; 1 Lithograph (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - The Old Bull Dog On the Right Track, 1864; 1 Lithograph. Previously folded in thirds, some tape on verso along one of the folds. Some foxing. (Box 76, Folder 1)
    Currier & Ives produced many of the important decorative prints of 19th century America. Their hand-colored lithographs covered a wide range of every phase of mid-century life and history, from city and country views, family life, portraits, comic prints, sports, etc., to political cartoons and newsworthy illustrations. These pictures were made by most of the celebrated artists of the time such as Thomas Nast, Otto Knirsch, Thomas Worth, as well as many others. Immensely popular and cheap, these prints were widely distributed but often mishandled and few survive today. Prints marked "N. Currier, N.Y." date from 1835 when Nathaniel Currier opened his lithographic shop until 1857 when James Ives became his partner and the firm's prints were marked "Published by Currier & Ives" from then on until the firm was liquidated in 1907. During that time the firm was carried on by the sons of the founders and flourished until the advent of chromolithography and photo-engraving in addition to the growing popularity of the illustrated newspaper caused their manual method of printing to become obsolete and unfashionable. (Source: Seller's note, see file)
  - The Siege of Plymouth A.D. 1874, circa 1874; 1 Lithograph. Double page spread; fold down middle causing possible separation of two halfs. All corners missing pieces; missing corners do not compromise artwork. (Box 76, Folder 1)
    Depiction of a battle scene with caption: The Siege of Plymouth A.D. 1874. A building in the background labeled Plymouth appears to be the Plymouth Congressional Church in Brooklyn, NY, which Henry Ward Beecher headed in 1874, when he was the subject of the Beecher-Tilton Scandal Case which culminated in an 1875 adultery trial for Beecher.
  - John Bull Making a New Batch of Ships to Send to the Lakes, circa 1814; 1 Etching. Black ink; not colored. (Box 76, Folder 10)
  - Progress of the War, 1846; 1 Lithograph (Box 76, Folder 10)
  - The Pedlar and his Pack or the Desperate Effort, an Over Balance, 1828; 1 Lithograph. Hand-colored (partially). Some wear and acidity at edges. Some mending tape used at edges of copy with more coloring. (Box 76, Folder 10)
    In the 1828 U.S. Presidential election supporters of candidate John Quincy Adams created and distributed anti-Jackson "coffin handbills" or coffin bills in an attempt to depict Andrew Jackson as too brutal and militaristic.
  - Don Quixote & Rocinante, circa 2004; 1 Engraving. Ink on paper. Artist signature in pencil with note of limited print numbering 7/100. (Box 76, Folder 11)
    Depiction of a soldier in partial armor with hat, holding a lance, carrying a shield, and sitting on an armored horse.
  - [Portfolio of cartoon prints by Harold Talburt with informational brochure and card from Scripps advertising department], 1943; Includes 24 prints in each portfolio. Includes a folder with 2 copies of a promotional brochure and 2 copies of a card from the advertising department at Scripps Howard before the 2 portfolios. (Box 76, Folder 14)
    Talburt's cartoons appeared in all of the Scripps-Howard papers, but he was based in DC on the Washington News.
    A collection of 24 cartoons, printed 18" x 15" and one to a sheet, along with a four-page promotional booklet, distributed to newspaper editors considering buying Talburt's cartoons. Subject matter includes President Franklin D. Roosevelt, the New Deal, the U.S. economy, federal government programs, World War II, Japan, Hitler and the Nazis, Mussolini and fascism.
  - [Untitled cartoon drawing of Senator Edward Kennedy driving former President Jimmy Carter (in scuba gear).], 1991; 1 Poster (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 14)
    Editorial cartoon print (6/20). Senator Edward Kennedy driving with Jimmy Carter (in scuba gear)in the back seat. Kennedy looks back at Carter suspiciously. Inscribed with pencil, "Oliphant 91".
  - [Untitled cartoon pencil drawing of an elephant (wearing a "76" jersey") and a peanut, sitting on opposite ends of a teeter totter.], 1976 May; 1 Drawing. Pencil on paper. (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 4)
  - Bad Dictators Our Enemies - Good Dictators Our Allies, circa 2005; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 7)
    A woman (possibly Condoleezza Rice) sits at a large desk with her hands folded and resting atop a desk blotter with a piece of paper while she twiddles her thumbs. She is flanked by two American flags and two file boxes marked "Bad Dictators Our Enemies" and "Good Dictators Our Allies".
  - Dear Mom and Dad, Happy New Year 2020!, circa 2003; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 6)
    An elderly soldier with an American flag tattoo and wearing a helmet marked US Army crouches in an alley behind an oil drum. He is writing a letter that says, "Dear Mom and Dad, Happy New Year 2020!" He is located in Iraq, which is evidenced by a nearby abandoned car's license plate marked "Iraq", and a background consisting of several minarets, a black helicopter flying overhead, and something unseen smoking and burning.
  - Dubya's Construction - Renovations. Nation building., circa 2003; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 9)
    A work truck marked "Dubya's Construction. Renovations. Nation Building." The truck is parked near a sidewalk, in front of a house labeled "Iran." A figure dressed as Uncle Sam stands in front of the house asking the occupant in the doorway, "I've been doin' some work in the neighborhood.... can I interest you in a free estimate?" Meanwhile, the two buildings to the left, labeled "Iraq" and "Afghanistan" have already been destroyed and smoke can be seen still smoldering in the rubble.
  - Election 2000, Sing [opera singer], 2000 November 14; 1 Digital print. Work is inscribed, "4/20 For Michael Kahn. Best wishes from Pat Oliphant MM [2000]" (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 13)
    Digital print, 4/20. Original editorial cartoon work by Pat Oliphant, Universal Press Syndicate, copyright 2000. Depicts a stage and audience at an opera. A woman (opera singer) dressed in Viking attire stands on the stage holding a spear in her left hand and a shield in her right hand with the text: Election 2000. She is viewed from behind looking toward audience while a man front and center holds a card reading "SING". Oliphant's character Punk is featured in lower right corner commenting, "This is the fat anti-defamation league!." Work is inscribed by creator in pencil, "4/20 For Michael Kahn. Best wishes from Pat Oliphant MM [2000]"
  - I, George W... (wink). Do solemnly swear... (wink), 2000 December 11; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 1)
    Digital print, 1 of 20. Original editorial cartoon work by Pat Oliphant, Universal Press Syndicate, copyright 2000. Depicts President George W. Bush standing in front of Chief Justice William Rehnquist at Bush's first inauguration. Rehnquist is performing the swearing in ceremony; Bush's left hand is placed on a Bible and his right hand is held up to take oath. Bush says" I, George W..." (wink) and Rehnquist replies, "Do solemnly swear..." (wink).Oliphant's character Punk is featured in lower right of panel commenting, "You wanna hear some solemn swearing?" Print is signed and inscribed in pencil by creator, "1/20. To Michael Kahn from Pat Oliphant MMI".
  - OKAY! Has anyone seen my wallet?, circa 2005; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 5)
    Kevin Kallaugher ("KAL") is an American political cartoonist for The Economist and the Baltimore Sun. He has contributed cartoons to many newspapers and magazines in the U.S., Britain, Australia, France, Germany, and around the world.
    Uncle Sam stands between two vacuums, holding his hat in his right hand and scratching his head with his left hand, asking, "Okay! Has anyone seen my wallet?" The oversized vacuums are pushed by members of the US Army and possibly the US Army Corp of Engineers. The soldier pushes a vacuum marked "Iraq" and the Corp member pushes a vacuum marked "Katrina". The vacuums are noisily (Vroooom! Slurp!) sucking up wads of cash and a sign in the foreground states "Caution Cleaning Under Way."
  - Stem Cells Research - Science, circa 2005; 1 Digital print (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 8)
    A hooded monk figure appears as an inquisitor, holding a torch in his right hand and wearing a large Christian cross around his neck. The torch is held toward a large stack of paper labeled "Stem Cells Research" while a distressed man in a lab coat wearing a sign marked "Science" stands tied up apparently about to be burnt at the stake like a witch or heretic.
  - Supreme Court - Roe v. Wade, 2005; 1 Drawing. Pen and black ink editorial cartoon drawing. Verso of paper includes draft of same cartoon in pencil. (Box 76, Folder 7, Item 12)
    Attached note has been separated to Notes file.
  - Greeley the Woodchopper. Or the end of the "present" term., 1872; 1 Lithograph (Box 76, Folder 8)
  - Jeff's Last Shift. Capture of Jeff Davis May 10th 1865 at Irwinsville, GA, circa 1865; 1 Print. Lithograph. (Box 76, Folder 8)
  - Why Don't You Take It?, 1861; 1 Print (Box 76, Folder 8)
    Currier & Ives produced many of the important decorative prints of 19th century America. Their hand- colored lithographs covered a wide range of every phase of mid-century life and history, from city and country views, family life, portraits, comic prints, sports, etc., to political cartoons and newsworthy illustrations. These pictures were made by most of the celebrated artists of the time such as Thomas Nast, Otto Knirsch, Thomas Worth, as well as many others. Immensely popular and cheap, these prints were widely distributed but often mishandled and few survive today. Prints marked "N. Currier, N.Y." date from 1835 when Nathaniel Currier opened his lithographic shop until 1857 when James Ives became his partner and the firm's prints were marked "Published by Currier & Ives" from then on until the firm was liquidated in 1907. During that time the firm was carried on by the sons of the founders and flourished until the advent of chromolithography and photo-engraving in addition to the growing popularity of the illustrated newspaper caused their manual method of printing to become obsolete and unfashionable. (Source: Seller's note, see file)
  - Harper's Pictorial History of the Civil War, Volume II - Chief Justices of the United States [single page 665], 1866; 1 Print (Box 76, Folder 9, Item 2)
    Single page 665 from Harper's Pictorial History of the Civil War, Volume II featuring hand-colored engraving illustration of Chief Justices of the United States from the chapter on Political Developments of 1864.
  - Salt River Gazette, circa 1879-1880; 1 Broadside. Single sheet broadside. (Box 76, Folder 9, Item 1)
    The Salt River Gazette was published in New York, N.Y. "Salt River" was a colloquial term for political misfortune or failure SOURCE: LOC
  - Humanity - October 1908 "Freedom's Shadow of Death", 1908 October; 1 Broadside (Box 78, Folder 11)
  - Shadows of the Times (1, 2, 3), circa 1862; 3 Lithographs. 3 different plate designs. (Box 78, Folder 11)
  - Struggle for the Presidency, circa 1839; 1 Lithograph. Foxing, missing the top left corner, not affecting artwork. (Box 78, Folder 11)
    A man rides a rearing horse, his top hat is flying behind him as he hangs onto the mane. At top text reads: The Start "tune" (Off She Goes). Caption reads: Struggle for the Presidency [the "SI" in presidency is crossed out in black ink and "CE" is written over the letters] between V.B...N and Black Bess, at New-York July 2, 1839, or Matty holding on to the Ma(I)ne Chance.
  - The First of May 1865 or Gen[era]l Moving Day in Richmond, VA, circa 1865; 1 Lithograph. 3 copies of same color print. All copies have either tears and/or flaking edges and acidity evident. (Box 78, Folder 11)
  - Climate Change is a Hoax, 2018 October 5; 1 Drawing. Editorial cartoon artwork (Box 78, Folder 12, Item 1-2)
    Original color editorial cartoon depicting a disgruntled looking man standing in a body of water holding a sign reading "Climate change is a hoax." He appears to be standing north of the Gulf of Mexico (possibly in Texas or Louisiana) while west of him, the United States is on fire or already burnt; to the east the clouds are pouring rain onto the land causing catastrophic flooding (people are shown drowning, homes and vehicles float in the water); additionally, fish and other marine life are shown dead, floating in the waters of the Gulf, Caribbean and Atlantic Ocean near Florida.
  - Where There's A Will..., 1980 February 24; 1 Print. Copy of ink drawing by Draper Hill inscribed and dated in black ink "For Michael K - Draper H." and signed by artist in red ink. (Box 78, Folder 12, Item 3)
    In the 1980 Winter Olympic Games, in Lake Placid, New York, the USA ice hockey team beat the Soviet team in a major upset deemed "The Miracle on Ice."
    Four ice hockey players in full gear ascend a grassy hill raising an American flag, reminiscent of the famous February 23, 1945 A.P. photograph by Joe Rosenthal entitled "Raising the Flag on Iwo Jima." The players' names and numbers are shown at least partially on their jerseys: Mark Wells (15), Dave Christian (23), Mark Johnson (10), and Jim Craig (30).
  - Jeff Davis Caught At Last. Hoop Skirts & Southern Chivalry., 1865; 1 Lithograph (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 8)
  - John Brown Exhibiting His Hangman!, 1865; 1 Lithograph (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 6)
  - John Bull and His Baltimoreans, 1814; 1 Lithograph. Ink on paper. (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 2)
  - Johnny Bull and the Alexandrians, 1814; 1 Etching. Hand-colored. Ink on paper. (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 1)
    The citizens of Alexandria, Virginia, are ridiculed in this scene for their lack of serious resistance against the British seizure of the city in 1814. (Source: LOC)
  - Suspending Specie Payments., circa 1837; 1 Specie Circular (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 5)
  - The "Rail Splitter" at Work Repairing the Union, 1865; 1 Lithograph. Some tears, missing 1.5 inch piece from left side and small piece from bottom of page. (Box 78, Folder 7, Item 4)
  - [Engraving of Theodore Roosevelt with slip sheet], 1907; 1 Engraving (Box 78, Folder 8)
  - [The Travelers calendar page illustration for September 1963, "Central Park, Winter. The Skating Carnival"], 1 Print (Box 78, Folder 8)
    Currier & Ives lithograph reproduction of a winter scene painting from approximately the 1860s, used to illustrate calendar page. Depicts a winter scene in what is likely the Northeastern United States.
  - [The Travelers Insurance Companies calendar page illustration for April 1974, "Winter in the Country (Chopping Wood)"], 1 Print (Box 78, Folder 8)
  - [Traveler's Insurance calendar page illustration for April 1951, "The Farm in Winter"], 1 Print (Box 78, Folder 8)
  - [Traveler's Insurance calendar page illustration for September 1957, "The Farmers Home - Winter"], 1 Print (Box 78, Folder 8)
  - Little Mac, In His Great Two Horse Act, In the Presidential Canvass of 1864, 1 Print (Box 78, Folder 9, Item 7)
  - Reciprocal trade. I place myself in the hands of my friends. Peace and plenty long shall reign, ere these three shall meet again., circa 1888; 1 Print (Box 80, Folder 10)
    Anti-Grover Cleveland cartoon. A man in a suit stands holding a note reading: Official Patronage in one hand. A large cat with an Australian flag tied to its tail is clawing at his arm. His other hand extends to grab British bank notes from the Bank of England from another (well-dressed) man in a suit and hat.
  - Congressional Pugilists, 1798; 1 Engraving (Box 80, Folder 2)
  - Hon. John Minor Botts, circa 1850; 1 Mezzotint (Box 80, Folder 2)
  - The prize calf "S.L. Woodford," fattened by messrs. Greeley and Curtis for the special purpose of being cut up on Tuesday, November 8th., 1870 October 29; 1 Newspaper Clipping (Box 80, Folder 2)
    Published in Punchinello on page 72, October 29, 1870 (Source: NYPL).
  - Confederate War Etchings of Adalbert J. Volck [29 prints contained within folders, contained within clamshell box], [along with] Sketches from the Civil War in North America... by V. Blada [reprint of 1917 descriptive booklet], [along with] Lincoln Herald, Fall 1954 [magazine containing 8 caricatures of Lincoln by Volck], circa 1892; 29 etchings printed on India paper individually contained in paper folders, boxed in morocco clamshell box. (Box 82, Folder 2)
    Includes guide summary page, reprint pages of Sketches from Civil War in North America, Lincoln Herald magazine and 29 prints.
  - We can gain no lasting peace if we approach it with suspicion and mistrust..., circa 1945; 1 Drawing. Pen and ink on paper with some white corrective paint or ink. Editorial pencil marks. Some tears, creases and dirt marks (Box 86, Folder 3)
    Depiction of the symbolic figure of Uncle Sam sitting in a desk chair reading a portion of text fromPresident Franklin Roosevelt's fourth inaugural address. His hat is resting upside down on the desk nearby. Figuresof George Washington and Abraham Lincoln are shown in the background.
  - Abe Linking With His Significantly Named Cabinet, 1864; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - An Au-gust Convention, 1866; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
    The National Union Convention met in Philadelphia in August 1866.
  - Bubble Bursting, circa 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Funeral of Loco Focoism, 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Political Balance, 1840; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Splitting the Party (The Entering Wedge), 1872; 1 Lithograph (Box 86, Folder 4)